Guide to the Leonard A. Maynard papers, 1940-1971.
Maynard, Leonard A. papers, 1940-1971
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Leonard A. Maynard papers, 1940-1971.
29-1-292
Leonard Amby, Maynard 1887-1972.
7.2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, academic papers, discussion notes
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Papers documenting Maynard's career at Cornell, including his involvement in establishing the School of Nutrition.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of Biochemistry and Nutrition; director of the School of Nutition,1941-1955; special consultant to the U.S. Interdepartmental Committee for Nutrition and National Defense.
After receiving his Ph.D. in chemistry from Cornell University in 1915 Leonard Amby Maynard was appointed assistant professor in the College of Agriculture there. In 1934 he served as visiting professor at the University of Nanking, China, and assisted in a survey of the nutrition of the Chinese farm family. At Cornell he directed the Animal Nutrition Laboratory and the U.S. Plant, Soil, and Nutrition Laboratory. He was named commissioner in charge of nutrition for the New York State Emergency Food Commission during World War II., and late in 1947 was appointed to a new food commission established by Governor Thomas E. Dewey. He wrote ANIMAL NUTRITION (1937); coauthored BETTER DAIRY FARMING with Elmer S. Savage; and wrote numerous publications on biochemistry and nutrition.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Included are administrative papers pertaining to four executive positions held by Professor Maynard (1940-49): director of the U.S. Plant, Soil, and Nutrition Laboratory, New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences (1940-45); director of the School of Nutrition, Cornell University (1941-49); head of the Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition, N.Y.S. College of Agriculture and Life Sciences (1945-49); and head of the Laboratory of Animal Nutrition, N.Y.S. College of Agriculture and Life Sciences (1940-49). Includes correspondence dealing with the establishment (1941) of the School of Nutrition and efforts to obtain financial support for it, administrative matters, nutrition research, the London Nutrition Conference (1951) and other professional meetings, Maynard's lecture invitations, and his evaluation of scientific manuscripts sent him; inquiries from individuals and institutions, with Maynard's replies, chiefly concerning the nutritive value of milk and enriched bread and of butter as opposed to margarine; and notes (June 1941) from discussions with President Edmund Ezra Day on the establishment of the School and notes (1951, 1952) relating to its present and future programs. Correspondents include Sanford S. Atwood, Howard E. Babcock, Cornelis W. de Kiewiet, Edward R. Eastman, Willard I. Emerson, Anson W. Gibson, David Birney Hand, Herman E. Hilleboe, Asa S. Knowles, Deane W. Malott, William I. Myers, Weyland Pfeiffer, and Fred Sexauer.
Also, an interview (114 page typescript, 1963) conducted in six sessions by Gould P. Colman, in which Maynard discusses his graduate work, the establishment of a chemical laboratory in the Department of Animal Husbandry, research and graduate instruction, nutrition studies at other institutions in the 1920s, work on open formula feeds and other studies done with the GLF (Cooperative Grange League Federation Exchange, Inc., now Agway), the administration of the U.S. Plant, Soil, and Nutrition Laboratory at Cornell, the development and administration of the Department of Biochemistry and the School of Nutrition, nutrition practices and study in China in 1934, England during World War II., Germany at the end of the war, and Central America and elsewhere following his retirement, the work of ICA and FAO (Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations), and his association with H. E. Babcock, J. Lossing Buck, Lewis Knudson, Albert R. Mann, and Elmer Seth Savage.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Maynard, Leonard Amby,1887-1972.; Atwood, Sanford S.; Babcock, Howard E.; Buck, John Lossing, 1890-; Day, Edmund Ezra, 1883-1951.; De Kiewiet, C. W. (Cornelius William), 1902-; Eastman, Edward R.; Emerson, Willard I.; Gibson, Anson Wright, 1892-1977.; Hand, David Birney.; Hilleboe, Herman E.; Knowles, Asa S.; Knudson, Lewis, 1884-1958.; Malott, Deane W. (Deane Waldo), 1898-; Mann, Albert Russell, 1880-1947.; Myers, William I.; Pfeiffer, Weyland.; Savage, Elmer Seth.; Sexauer, Fred H.; Lilly Endowment; American Association for the Advancement of Science; Cornell Nutrition Conference; Edward S. Foster; Farm Bureau Federation of Ithaca; Federal Security Agency; Public Health Service; National Council of Farmer Cooperative; C.E.F. Guterman; Hoblitzelle Award; Harrell Heath News; Cooperative Grange League Federation Exchange.; Cornell University. School of Nutrition.; Food and Agriculture Organization of the United Nations.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences. Department of Biochemistry and Nutrition.; New York State College of Agriculture and Life Sciences. Department of Animal Husbandry.; U.S. Plant, Soil, and Nutrition Laboratory.
Subjects:
Biochemistry.; Nutrition--Central America.; Nutrition--China.; Nutrition--England.; Nutrition--Germany.; Biochemists.; College teachers.; Nutritionists.
Places:
China.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
RELATED MATERIALS
Includes collection #21-1-292.
CONTAINER LIST
- Correspondence, A-Z (Box 1)
- School of Nutrition correspondence, A-Z, 1941-1949 (Box 2)
- School of Nutrition files: Research reports done for Consolidation Edison Co. (Box 3)
- Correspondence of Laboratory of Animal Nutrition, A-Z (Box 3)
- Biochemistry and Nutrition correspondence, files A-W (Box 4)
- Leonard A. Maynard's Manuscripts for publication; correspondence and publications of various organizations and subjects (Box 4)
- ICNND - Finance Records (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Leung, 1971 (Box 5, Folder 2)
- Food Composition - Africa (Box 5, Folder 3)
- Southeast Asia
  - Nutrition History - Reprints (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Food Composition - Far East (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Outline, References, Biog. Sources (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Early History (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - History - Organizations - Journals S.N. 520 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Energy Metabolism, Animal Calorimetry (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Proteins and Amino Acids (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Digestion, Feeding Standards (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Calcium and Phosphorus (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Other Minerals (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Vitamins (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - Miscellaneous Notes not Included in Lectures (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - Aristotle and others (Box 5, Folder 16)
- History of Nutrition Course - Background
  - Biographies (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Introduction (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - Professor Verzar (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence - McCay (Box 5, Folder 20)
  - Library Call Numbers, etc. (Box 5, Folder 21)
  - McCay History (Miscellaneous Related Notes) (Box 5, Folder 22)
  - Mrs. C.M. McCay (Box 5, Folder 23)
  - Food Commission (Box 5, Folder 24)
  - Letters of Transmittal and Replies - History of the School (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 26)
  - Food Enrichment (Box 5, Folder 27)
  - Babcock Memorial Fund - DeGraff as Professor (Box 5, Folder 28)
  - Notes from L.A.M. Archives (Box 5, Folder 29)
  - Savage Hall Construction and Dedication (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Data on Beginnings (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Frozen Food Research (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - State Appropriation Fund-Raising Program (Box 5, Folder 33)
  - Geer Research Fellowship (Box 5, Folder 34)
  - Early Years of the Graduate School of Nutrition at Cornell, by Leonard A. Maynard, 1941-1956 (Box 5, Folder 35-36)
  - Miscellaneous Documents and Summaries (Box 5, Folder 37)
- History of School
  - History - Comments of Reviewers (Box 5, Folder 38)
  - Maynard. Report of Chairman of Standing Committee on Nutrition, Ninth Pacific Science Congress (Box 5, Folder 39)
  - UK System vs. Atwater, S and D article Letters to Matt, 1970-1971 (Box 5, Folder 40)
  - History of Institute of Nutrition - Correspondence (Box 5, Folder 41)
  - American Institute of Nutrition (Box 5, Folder 42)
  - Animal Efficiency (Box 5, Folder 43)
  - Wesleyan (Box 5, Folder 44)
  - Ab Antibiotics (Box 5, Folder 45)
  - Data from Stevens on Cellulose Metabolism (Box 5, Folder 46)
  - Medlar's Bibliography on Cellulose Metabolism (Box 5, Folder 47)
  - Calcitonin (Box 5, Folder 48)
  - Calcium Phosphorous CaP (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Carbohydrates CAR (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - The Calorie Content of Urine of Human Beings and the Estimation of Metabolizable Energy of Foodstuffs (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Energy-Yielding Components of Food and Computation of Calorie Values (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Notes on Calculation of Energy Values, 1965-1971 (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - EN Energetics (animals) (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - EN Discussion of the Terms Digestibility. Availability and Fuel Value. W.O. Atwater Storrs Report, 1899 (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - Available Carbohydrates Atwater System of Calculating the Caloric Value of Diets (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - Food Standards (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - FF Feeds, Foods (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Physiology - Pathology PP (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Protein P (Box 5, Folder 60)
  - Reproduction (Box 5, Folder 61)
  - S.P.N. Soil - Plant - Nutrition (Box 5, Folder 62)
  - Guide to terminology in Biomedical Res. (Box 5, Folder 63)
  - Teaching T (Box 5, Folder 64)
  - Vitamin D VD (Box 5, Folder 65)
  - V (Box 5, Folder 66)
  - Vitamin E VE (Box 5, Folder 67)
  - VPan. Pantothenic Acid (Box 5, Folder 68)
  - VCH Choline (Box 5, Folder 69)
  - Vitamin B6 (Box 5, Folder 70)
  - Vitamin A VA (Box 5, Folder 71)
  - Vitamin B VB (Box 5, Folder 72)
  - Vitamin B12 VB12 (Box 5, Folder 73)
  - Vitamins V (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Michigan Studies of Soil Effect on Milk SPN (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Water (Box 5, Folder 76)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence and Documents, 1941-1952 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, some 1950, 1952 included (Box 6, Folder 1A.)
  - Application Lilly Endowment, Inc; 813 Merch. Bk. Bld., Indianapolis 4, Ind. (weight and nutrition 1951) (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - 118th American Association for the Advancement of Science Meeting, Philadelphia, 1951. Correspondence 1951 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Nutrition Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 6, Folder 3B.)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 3C.)
  - Cornell Nutrition Feed Conference, Buffalo, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 6, Folder 4D.)
  - 1951, E.R. Eastman (Amer. Agr.) W.I. Emerson, V.P., Univ. Development (Box 6, Folder 4E.)
  - 1951-1952, Emerson- Fund Raising Program (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - 1951 Foster, Edward S., General Secretary N.Y.S. Farm Bureau Fed., Ithaca. Federal Security Agency, Public Health Service, Application for Grant (Box 7, Folder 5F.)
  - National Council of Farmer Cooperatives, Chicago, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 6G.)
  - Gibson, A.W., Director Resident Instruction, Roberts Hall, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Guterman, C.E.F., Director Agricultural Experiment Station, Roberts Hall, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Hoblitzelle Award, New York Regional Committee, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Harrell Heath News- Albany. Nutritional Broadsides, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Dr. David B. Hand, Agricultural Experiment Station 1951 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 11H.)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 11J.)
  - Correspondence 1951 (Box 7, Folder 11K.)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 11L.)
  - London Conference, Jan.-Feb. 1951 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - London Conference, Nov.-Dec. 1951 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 7, Folder 13M.)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 13Mc.)
  - Manuscripts and Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Dean W.I. Myers Correspondence, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - Memoranda, 1951 (Box 7, Folder 16)
  - Prof. L.C. Norris, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 17N.)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 17O.)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 17P.)
  - Correspondence with President, Malott, D.W.; Act. Wright, T.P.; act. de Kiewiet, C.W. 1951 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - Weyland Pfeiffer, 1951 Correspondence (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 19R.)
  - Correspondence, 1951-1952 (Box 8, Folder 19S.)
  - Science Service 1951 (Box 8, Folder 20)
  - Prof. Sumner, J.B., 1951 (Box 8, Folder 21)
  - Symposium- School Lunch Program, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 22)
  - Francis H. Scheetz- Ozonizers, 1946-1951 (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Task Force- School, 1950 (Box 8, Folder 24)
  - Incoming Telegrams, 1949-1951 (Box 8, Folder 25)
  - Outgoing Telegrams, 1949-1951 (Box 8, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1950 (Box 8, Folder 26V.)
  - Correspondence Dean E.L. Vincent, 1949-1950 (Box 8, Folder 27)
  - Correspondence, 1950-1951 (Box 8, Folder 27W.)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 27Y.)
  - Correspondence, 1951 (Box 8, Folder 27Z.)
- "Early Years of the graduate School of Nutrition at Cornell, 1941-1956 ." Published by the Graduate School of Nutrition, Cornell University, in 1968, giving an history of the establishment of the School of Nutrition in 1941. 104 page pamphlet (Box 9)
- Historical notes by Leonard Maynard (copy), 1950-1069; letter, Howard E. Babcock to James McConnell re the School of Nutrition, Feb. 9, 1950. (Box 9)
- 1 folder of correspondence, 1964-1969. (Box 10)
- Partial reprint set of L.A. Maynard's articles; 1918, 1928-1963. (Box 10)